Fernanda Ramirez-Espinoza

CONTACT Pontificia Universidad Católica Phone/WhatsApp: (+56) 9 9969 1176

Information JPAL-LAC E-mail: framireze@g.harvard.edu Instituto de Economía WWW: www.ramirezespinoza.com

Av. Vicuña MacKenna 4860,

Santiago, Chile

CURRENT JPAL-LAC — Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile APPOINTMENTS Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Departemento de Ingenierá Industrial - Pontificio Universidad Catálica de Chile

Departamento de Ingeniería Industrial— Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

Profesora Instructora Ago. 2022 -

Jun 2022 -

Research Affiliate - ConsiliumBots Jan. 2020 -

Social Impact Fellow – Agency Fund Dec. 2021- Ago. 2022

EDUCATION Ph.D. Educational Policy and Program Evaluation, Harvard University May 2022

Committee: Eric Taylor (chair), Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Michela Carlana, Christopher Neilson

Master in Education – International Education Policy, Harvard University

May 2021

Master in Public Policy, Harvard University

May 2017

M.S. in Engineering Science, Applied Microeconomics, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile Maximum distinction

Nov. 2011

B.S. in Industrial Engineering, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

Maximum Distinction Nov. 2010

Diploma in Transportation Engineering, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

Maximum Distinction Nov. 2010

RESEARCH Gender Gaps in STEM, Socioeconomic Diversity in STEM, Labor Economics, Economics of Educa-INTERESTS tion, Applied Microeconomics, Educational Policy, Program Evaluation.

RESEARCH IN "Role Models and the STEM Gender Gap" (Designed RCT, about to be in the field, Principal Progress Investigator)

"Gender Peer Effects in Post-Secondary Vocational Education" - Working paper Annenberg Series

"Gender Confidence Differences and the College Major Gap": Finished RCT, data analysis in progress AEA RCT registry, Principal Investigator

"Personalized Information Provision: Does Gender Play a Role?" (With Christopher Neilson)

"Closing Gaps in Higher Education Trajectories: The Effect of Targeted Information and Mentorship": RCT in progress (co-PI with Andrés Fernández-Barrios)

"Reinforcing the STEM pipeline in vocational-technical schools: Do female teachers matter?" (with Paola Bordón and Paola Sevilla)

"Do Cohort Peer Diversity Matters and For Whom? Evidence from Chile on Students' Academic

Outcomes". (With Francisco Lagos)

"Textbook Gender Bias and Educational Gender Gap"

"Providing Relative Performance Information in Colombia: Effects on Beliefs" (Principal Investigator)

"School admissions: Allocation Algorithms and Its Effects on school Segregation". (With Gabriel Gutirrez, Isidora Palma, and Francisco Lagos)

AWARDS, HONORS AND GRANTS

Social Impact Fellowship (\$65,000) - Agency Fund SPC (2021)

Independent Experience Stipend - David Rockefeller Center for Latin American Studies (2021)

Jens Aubrey Westengard Summer Research and Travel Grant, Harvard GSAS (2019)

Jens Aubrey Westengard Summer Research and Travel Grant, Harvard GSAS (2018)

Graduate School of Arts and Sciences Ph.D. Fellowship (2017–2019)

Carnesale Fellowship – Harvard Kennedy School (2015-2017)

Luksic Abaroa Fellowship for Chilean Students – Harvard Kennedy School (2015-2017)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Inter-American Development Bank, Washington DC, USA

Education Division Research Consultant

September, 2019 - December 2020

Harvard University

 $Research\ Assistant\ -\ Professor\ Emmerich\ Davies$

June, 2018 - Sept 2018

Harvard Graduate School of Education

 $Research\ Assistant\ -\ Professor\ Joshua\ Goodman$

Harvard Kennedy School of Government

May 2018

Princeton University

 $Research\ Assistant\ -\ Professor\ Christopher\ Nielson$ Economics Department

June, 2016 - August 2016

CONFERENCE AND PRESENTATIONS

STEM Gender Peer Effects in Post-Secondary Vocational Education:

- Universidad Alberto Hurtado, Seminario de Economía. March 2022.
- Universidad Diego Portales, Seminario de Economía. December 2021.
- Universidad del Pacífico (Perú), Seminario de Economía. December 2021.
- Graduate Students in Economics of Education (GEEZ), Zoom Seminar. November 2021.
- Ciclo de Seminario Económicos, FEN, Universidad de Talca. November, 2021
- Ridge LACEA Labor, Online (Covid-19), 9-10 December, 2020.
- Encuentro Sociedad Chilena de Políticas Públicas, Santiago, Chile, January 2020.
- (Cancelled due to COVID-19): Society for Research on Educational Effectiveness (SREE), Arlington, Virginia, USA, March, 2020.
- (Cancelled due to COVID-19): Association for Education Finance and Policy (AEFP), Fort Worth, Texas, USA, March, 2020.
- Association for Public Policy Analysis & Management (APPAM), Denver, Colorado, USA, November, 2019.

 Harvard Graduate School of Education Doctoral Colloquium, Harvard University, October 2019.

Information provision and STEM enrollment

- Association for Education Finance and Policy (AEFP), Denver, Colorado, USA, March, 2022.
- Encuentro Sociedad Chilena de Políticas Públicas, Santiago, Chile, January 2022.
- Harvard Graduate School of Education Doctoral Colloquium, Harvard University, October 2021.

Gender Bias in Textbooks:

• Association for Public Policy Analysis & Management (APPAM), Online, March 27-29 2021.

Socioeconomic Diversity Peer Effects:

 American Educational Research Association (AERA) Annual Meeting, Online, April 8-12, 2021.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Instructor, Departamento de Ingeniería Civil Industrial/PUC

- Applied Econometrics (Fall '22)

Instructor, Harvard Graduate School of Education

- Educational Policy in Developing Countries: Reviewing Impact Evaluations (Spring '22)

Teaching Fellow, Harvard Graduate School of Education

- Using Data in Organization (Prof. Carrie Conaway, Spring '21)
- The Politics of Education in Developing Countries (Prof. Emmerich Daviers, Fall '20)
- Applied Data Analysis (Prof. Andrew Ho, Spring '20)
- Microeconomics of Education (Prof. F. Barrera-Osorio, Fall '18 & Fall '19)
- The Consequences of Educational Policy Interventions in Developing Countries (Prof. F. Barrera-Osorio, Spring '19)

Teaching Assistant, Kennedy School of Government (9/2017 - 12/2017)

- Economic Analysis of Public Policy (Prof. Mark Shepard, Spring '17)

Teaching Fellow, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile (2007 – 2010)

- Optimization (2009-2010, 4 semesters)
- Introduction to Economics (2007-2008, 3 semesters)
- Calculus II (2007, 1 semester, Instituto de Economía)

SERVICE

Research Doctoral Advice Committee (2019-2020)

Founder and President of the Harvard Association of Chilean Students (2018-2019) Founder and President of the Chilean Caucus (Harvard Kennedy School) (2017-2018)

Professional Experience

Chief of Mission, Fundación América Solidaria, Port Au Prince, Haiti (2014 - 2015)

Cofounder and Board Member, Fundación Educación 2020, Santiago, Chile (August, 2012 - Jan, 2014)

Staff Professional - Plan de Formación de Directores de Excelencia, Ministry of Education, Santiago, Chile (2012)

OTHER SKILLS Programming languages: R, Stata, LATEX.

Languages: Spanish (Native), English (Fluent), Portuguese (Intermediate), Haitian Creole (Basic),

French (Basic).

References Eric Taylor, Associate professor, Harvard Graduate School of Education (eric_taylor@gse.harvard.edu)

Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Associate Professor of Public Policy, Education and Economics, Vanderbilt

University (felipe.barrera.-.osorio@vanderbilt.edu)

Christopher Neilson, Assistant Professor of Economics at Princeton (cneilson@princeton.edu)